Oh, that mansion.
Och, ta willa.
It's at the top of that hill.
Jest na szczycie wzgórza.
I see. Thank you.
Rozumiem. Dziękuję.
No problem.
Nie ma za co.
Roses, eh?
Róże, tak?
Just like the palace in Sleeping Beauty.
Niczym pałac w Śpiącej królewnie.
My name is Anna.
Mam na imię Anna.
Anna Liebert.
Anna Liebert.
Best of luck, mister great detective.
Powodzenia, panie superdetektywie.
She was worried that something awful might happen to you.
Bałam się, że spotka pana coś strasznego.
You see, I feel the same way that your mother feels.
Czuję to samo, co pana matka.
Anna…
Anna…
Were you just dreaming,
Właśnie pan śnił,
Detective Suk?
detektywie Suk?
Huh? Who are you?
Kim pan jest?
I'm Lunge, an inspector with the BKA.
Lunge, inspektor z Federalnego Biura Śledczego.
The BKA?
Z niemieckiego BKA?
It's okay. You can relax.
W porządku. Niech pan się nie stresuje.
I didn't come here to arrest you.
Nie przyszedłem pana aresztować.
This is quite a nice hospital room.
Całkiem przyjemny szpital.
I went to several hospitals with connections
Odwiedziłem kilka szpitali z powiązaniami
to the former Czechoslovakia secret police before I found you here.
z byłą czechosłowacką bezpieką, zanim tu pana znalazłem.
You're being treated quite well.
Całkiem dobrze się panem opiekują.
You must be very important to the former secret police.
Musi pan być dla nich kimś ważnym.
No, I was simply--
Nie, po prostu…
I already know all about you.
Już wszystko o panu wiem.
The beating death of Inspector Zeman who had connections with the secret police.
O pobiciu na śmierć inspektora Zemana i jego związkach z bezpieką.
The poisoning deaths of the commissioner
O otruciu komisarza
and two detectives of Prague Police Station.
i dwóch śledczych z praskiej komendy.
The shooting deaths of the two detectives who were tailing you.
O zastrzeleniu dwóch detektywów, którzy pana śledzili.
You're being pursued as a person of interest in all these murders.
Jest pan podejrzany o te wszystkie morderstwa.
Judging from just circumstantial evidence, you're the murderer in all these cases.
Dowody poszlakowe wskazują, że jest pan ich sprawcą.
You're wrong. I didn't do any of those things!
Jest pan w błędzie! To nie ja!
Then was it the tall man, Grimmer,
Zatem winny jest wysoki mężczyzna, Grimmer,
who Inspector Zeman questioned before he was beaten to death?
którego inspektor Zeman przesłuchiwał przed śmiercią?
It wasn't Mr. Grimmer either! He's not that kind of person!
Nie był to też Grimmer! Nie jest taki!
Then who is the murderer?
Zatem kto jest mordercą?
I bet you know, don't you?
Założę się, że pan wie, prawda?
I bet you know who the murderer is.
Zna pan tożsamość mordercy.
That's ridiculous.
Absurd. Gdybym wiedział, nie byłbym w tym stanie.
I've been betrayed over and over.
Co rusz mnie zdradzano.
I've been framed for murder and the police are after me now.
Wrobiono mnie w morderstwo i policja mnie ściga.
I've had enough of this. I'm sick of being stabbed in the back!
Mam tego dość. Ktoś mi wciąż wbija nóż w plecy!
You're a detective, right?
Jest pan śledczym.
As a detective, you must calmly dissect and investigate everything.
A śledczy musi spokojnie przeanalizować i sprawdzić wszystko.
Even at the cost of your happiness,
Nawet kosztem własnego szczęścia.
you must keep a level head as you dig up the truth.
Szukając prawdy, trzeba zachować trzeźwy osąd.
If you don't want to be betrayed anymore,
Jeśli nie chce pan już być zdradzanym,
then suspect the person you least want to suspect.
konieczna jest czujność wobec osoby, którą podejrzewa pan najmniej.
Who said you could see him?
Kto pozwolił panu go odwiedzić?
Bring me to your boss.
Chcę spotkać szefa.
Tell him I want to talk about the rose mansion.
Powiedz mu, że chcę porozmawiać o willi róż.
I know he'll want to talk to me about that.
Wiem, że zechce się spotkać w tej sprawie.
The Rose Mansion
ROZDZIAŁ 50 WILLA RÓŻ
Inspector Lunge of the BKA.
Inspektor Lunge z BKA.
I've checked out who you are and about your past.
Sprawdziłem pana i pana przeszłość.
I've also
Znam też
heard all kinds of rumors about you during the old regime, Captain Ranke.
całą masę pogłosek o pana działalności za czasów starego reżimu.
I've heard you're also the de facto leader of
Jest pan ponoć rzeczywistym liderem byłej czechosłowackiej bezpieki.
Things have been quite difficult for you recently.
Miał pan ostatnio sporo problemów.
Thank you for your concern.
Doceniam troskę.
I'm envious of people like you who can take long vacations.
Zazdroszczę takim jak pan, którzy mogą jechać na długi urlop.
I heard that two years ago,
Słyszałem, że dwa lata temu
your aggressive investigation of the secretary of Representative Boltzmann,
pana agresywne śledztwo skończyło się samobójstwem
You have to be more skillful than that to get far in this world.
Trzeba być zręczniejszym, by zajść daleko w świecie.
You and your people were foolish.
Działaliście nieroztropnie.
If you'd taken a softer line during democratization
Łagodniejsze podejście do demokratyzacji
and had managed your secrecy,
i lepsze zarządzanie tajnością,
you could be leading this country now as the shadow president.
a mógłby pan rządzić tym krajem jako jego zakulisowy prezydent.
But now, the fear that the public has of your people is just an illusion.
Obecny lęk opinii publicznej przed wami to tylko iluzja.
I see. You're quite sharp.
Rozumiem. Jest pan dość bystry.
So, what brings you and your smarts to me?
Co sprowadza pana ze swoim sprytem do mnie?
As you already know, I'm on an extended vacation,
Jak pan wie, jestem na dłuższym urlopie.
so I'm partly here for pleasure.
Po części jestem tu dla rozrywki.
I'm looking for something.
Szukam czegoś.
I'm looking for the embodiment of true fear.
Szukam ucieleśnienia prawdziwego strachu.
I want to know if a true demon was born
Chcę wiedzieć, czy narodził się prawdziwy demon
out of the illusion that you people created.
z iluzji, którą stworzyliście.
So, this is about the Red Rose Mansion.
Czyli chodzi o Willę Czerwonych Róż.
I had to search quite a lot before I found that mansion.
Namęczyłem się, zanim znalazłem tę willę.
That's because the author of this book had many pen names.
Dlatego że autor tej książki miał wiele pseudonimów literackich.
The Nameless Monster.
Bezimienny potwór.
The author's name is Emil Scherbe
Autor nazywa się Emil Scherbe.
His address was an apartment in an old building in Prague.
Jego adres to lokal w starej praskiej kamienicy.
A different company is renting it now.
Wynajmuje go teraz inna firma.
The address for Klaus Poppe is an old farm house in the suburbs.
Adres Klausa Poppego to stara chałupa na przedmieściach.
But it's already been torn down.
Została już jednak zburzona.
Jakob Vyrobek's address is also just a rental space.
Adres Jakoba Vyrobka to przestrzeń na wynajem.
But you eventually found…
Ale ostatecznie znalazł pan…
Franz Bonaparta?
Franza Bonapartę?
What is it with that mansion?
O co chodzi z tą willą?
Who is Franz Bonaparta?
Kim jest Franz Bonaparta?
No matter how much I search, I can't find anything on him.
Nieważne, ile szukam, nie ma żadnego jego śladu.
Which can only mean that he was one of your people,
Czyli musiał był jednym z waszych ludzi,
a member of the former Czechoslovakia secret police.
członkiem byłej czechosłowackiej bezpieki.
What do you want to know?
Co chce pan wiedzieć?
I want to know what you know.
Chcę wiedzieć to, co pan.
I know nothing.
Nic nie wiem.
Except…
Poza tym, że…
Yes?
Tak?
I've consciously tried to forget it.
Świadomie próbowałem o tym zapomnieć.
I have consciously tried to forget about that mansion.
Świadomie próbowałem zapomnieć o tej willi.
That's why I've never touched or messed with it,
Dlatego jej nie ruszałem
and why it still stands there.
i wciąż stoi opuszczona.
All the political prisoners who were brought there
Przebywający tam więźniowie polityczni
and all the researchers who were there disappeared one day.
i wszyscy naukowcy pewnego dnia zniknęli.
That's all I know.
To wszystko, co wiem.
What is that wall?
Co to za ściana?
What wall?
Jaka ściana?
The other day, I went inside that mansion.
Ostatnio wszedłem do willi.
There's no sign of anyone having entered it.
Nie było śladu niczyjej obecności.
It's completely abandoned. However,
Była całkiem opuszczona, jednakże… po północnej stronie drugiego piętra
there's a wall that looks as if it was hastily put up to shut something inside.
była ściana. Wyglądała na pośpiesznie postawioną,
Can I tear down that wall?
Mogę zburzyć tę ścianę?
What are you frightened of, Captain Ranke?
Czego się pan boi, kapitanie Ranke?
You just might die.
Może pan nawet zginąć.
If you get any closer to it,
Kto się do tego zbliży,
both you and I…
czy to pan, czy ja…
might see what true fear is.
może poznać, czym jest prawdziwy strach.
Franz Bonaparta, eh?
Franz Bonaparta?
I haven't heard that name in a long time.
Dawno nie słyszałem tego imienia.
Do you take milk or sugar in your coffee?
Kawa z mlekiem albo cukrem?
It's fine black.
Czarna może być.
Is something wrong?
Coś nie tak?
No. I'm just surprised that a fan of Franz Bonaparta has suddenly shown up.
Nie. Dziwię się, że nagle zjawił się fan Franza Bonaparty.
I heard about you from Moravia Publishing.
Wydawnictwo Moravia podało mi pana namiar.
Mr. Sovák,
Panie Sovák,
I heard you were Mr. Bonaparta's editor for a long time.
ponoć przez wiele lat był pan redaktorem pana Bonaparty.
Yes.
Tak.
But I was only his editor
Ale byłem tylko jego redaktorem,
when he worked under the pen name Klaus Poppe.
kiedy pisał pod pseudonimem literackim Klaus Poppe.
I'd like to know what kind of person he was.
Chciałbym poznać, jakim był człowiekiem.
Franz Bonaparta, huh?
Franz Bonaparta?
He would come to my home here to discuss his work.
Odwiedzał mnie w domu, żeby omawiać swoją pracę.
He would sit in that chair there just like you are.
Siedział na tamtym krześle. Tak jak pan teraz.
He'd often play in the garden with my daughter too.
Często bawił się w ogrodzie z moją córką.
But at the time, my daughter said something odd.
Powiedziała mi wtedy coś dziwnego:
She said, "That man is frightening."
„To przerażający człowiek”.
But I doubt my daughter remembers anything now
Wątpię, żeby córka to pamiętała,
from when she was that young.
bo była bardzo młoda.
Was he a member of a government agency then?
Czy należał do agencji rządowej?
He probably was. I figured he was when I worked with him.
Zapewne. Takie miałem podejrzenie, gdy z nim współpracowałem.
But his demeanor and the way he talked and dressed
Jego postawa, styl mówienia i ubierania
had a gentleness and gracefulness that was uncommon
miały w sobie niecodzienną grację i delikatność
among government officials in the old regime.
jak na oficjela starego reżimu.
Bonaparta had a doctorate in psychiatry and was also a psychologist.
Bonaparta miał doktorat z psychiatrii, był też psychologiem.
He specialized in neurosurgery.
Specjalizował się w neurochirurgii.
Oh… I see.
Rozumiem.
Let's see, when did I last see him?
Kiedy ostatni raz go widziałem?
I think it was the summer of either 1981 or 1982.
Bodajże latem 1981 lub 1982 roku.
That day, he suddenly dropped by here.
Wpadł do mnie bez zapowiedzi.
He talked about his idea for a new book.
Mówił o pomysłach na nową książkę.
I remember now. He appeared rather energetic.
Już pamiętam. Wydawał się bardzo rozentuzjazmowany.
What was the new story about?
O czym była nowa opowieść?
It was about a monster who falls in love.
O potworze, który się zakochuje.
It was like a mix of Sleeping Beauty and Beauty and the Beast.
Takie połączenie Śpiącej królewny z Piękną i bestią.
I rejected it.
Odrzuciłem ją.
Then just before he left, when he was at the door,
A tuż przed wyjściem, gdy stał w drzwiach,
he said, "Oh, I know. How about this?"
powiedział: „Wiem. A co pan na to?”.
Then he turned around and said,
Odwrócił się i rzekł:
"A story about a door that must never be opened."
„Opowieść o drzwiach, których nigdy nie należy otwierać”.
I asked him,
Zapytałem go:
"Is there a paradise beyond it? Or does a monster come out?"
„Znajduje się tam raj? Czy potwór się z nich wyłoni?”
Then he said,
Odparł:
"No. Since it must never be opened, I guess it won't make much of a story."
„Nie. Skoro nie można ich otworzyć, marna chyba będzie z tego opowieść”.
After saying that, he laughed and left.
Potem się roześmiał i wyszedł.
That was the last time I saw him.
Wtedy zobaczyłem go po raz ostatni.
Did you find anything significant about this Bonaparta guy?
Dowiedział się pan coś istotnego w sprawie tego Bonaparty?
No, I didn't learn much.
Nie, nic godnego uwagi.
Mr. Grimmer, what are you doing here?
A pan co tutaj robi?
I was just admiring the nice weather.
Podziwiam piękną pogodę.
Yes, it sure is.
Rzeczywiście ładna.
I knew it.
Wiedziałem.
Hello? Police?
Halo? Policja?
I'm Sovák. I live near Schwaig Square.
Mówi Sovák. Mieszkam na Placu Schwaig.
A man just came to my place
Był u mnie mężczyzna,
who I think is wanted as a person of interest
który zdaje się być podejrzanym w sprawie seryjnych morderstw w Niemczech.
Yes, he was Japanese. That neurosurgeon Dr. Tenma.
Tak, Japończyk. Neurochirurg doktor Tenma.
Ethanol?
Etanol.
It smells like disinfectant.
Pachnie środkiem dezynfekującym.
Death… Several people… died here.
Śmierć… Zmarło tu kilka osób.
Ten people…
Dziesięć osób…
Maybe 20…
Może 20…
No, even more.
Nie, nawet więcej.
That woman…
Ta kobieta…
She's the one from the sketchbook.
To ją narysowano w szkicowniku.
The mother of those twins.
To matka tych bliźniąt.
Hey, if we don't hurry, the older kids will take the soccer field!
Pośpieszmy się, zanim starszaki przejmą boisko!
Hurry up, Milosz!
Szybko, Miloszu!
Okay.
Dobra.
Go! Counter attack!
Dalej! Kontratak!
Oh no! Pull back! They're charging for the goal!
O nie! Do tyłu! Pędzą na bramkę!
Oh no! They'll score!
O nie! Strzelą!
Go!
Dalej!
-Woah! -Milosz!
- Rany! - Miloszu!
You okay, Milosz?
Nic ci nie jest? Obudź się, Miloszu!
Nice save, Milosz!
Ale parada, Miloszu!
Way to clear it! You stopped them from scoring!
Ale żeś obronił! Powstrzymałeś gola!
-What? -Way to go, Milosz!
- Co? - Brawo, Miloszu!
He's smiling. I guess he's all right now.
Uśmiecha się, więc chyba ma się dobrze.
What do you think, Dr. Tenma?
Co pan myśli, doktorze Tenma.
I agree.
Zgoda.
Mr. Grimmer, aren't you going to talk to Milosz and the other kids?
Panie Grimmer, nie pogada pan z Miloszem i resztą dzieci?
I figured out why I'm not good at soccer.
Już wiem, dlaczego jestem kiepski w piłkę.
I'm not a team player.
Nie potrafię grać drużynowo.
What happens to Detective Jan Suk now?
Co z detektywem Janem Sukiem?
He's wanted as a person of interest in the murders,
Jest poszukiwany jako podejrzany o morderstwa,
which is the same as being kicked out of society.
co jest równoważne ze społecznym wykluczeniem.
Even if he turned himself in, how could he prove his innocence?
Nawet jeśli odda się w ręce władz, jak miałby udowodnić swoją niewinność?
How can he prove the existence of this blonde woman who left the scene?
Jak udowodni istnienie blondynki, która opuściła miejsce zbrodni?
He's in the same situation as you are.
Jest w tej samej sytuacji co pan.
But there is one difference.
Z jedną różnicą.
I'll be seeing you, Dr. Tenma.
Do zobaczenia, doktorze Tenma.
What?
Co?
As for these murders,
Jeśli chodzi o te morderstwa,
there is one person who knows all the particulars about them.
jedna osoba zna każdy jej szczegół.
He's right here.
Stoi tutaj.
What if I sent something like this to the police?
A może wysłałbym coś takiego policji?
What's this?
Co to jest?
It's a letter from a serial murderer.
List od seryjnego mordercy.
It's a detailed description of things that have been kept secret
To szczegółowy opis utajnionych rzeczy,
that only the real murderer could know.
które wiedziałby tylko morderca.
But if you send this to the police, then you'll be arrested!
Aresztują cię, jeśli wyślesz to policji!
This Grimmer person will somehow make his way back to Germany.
Grimmer jakoś wróci do Niemiec.
I'm sure the police will come after him,
Policja na pewno zechce go złapać,
but this Grimmer guy will be able to get away from them.
ale ten Grimmer potrafi im się wymknąć.
You see, he was originally quite a talented spy.
Widzi pan, pierwotnie był całkiem utalentowanym szpiegiem.
But you'll end up being a suspect on the run your whole life!
Ale będzie pan uciekać do końca życia!
I don't mind.
Nie szkodzi.
You see, this Grimmer person never really existed anyway.
Grimmer tak naprawdę nigdy nie istniał.
He's a person someone forced me to be.
Ktoś zmusił mnie, żebym nim był.
Even if Grimmer is suspected of murder all his life,
Nawet gdyby Grimmera ścigano do końca życia,
it doesn't bother me at all.
nie przeszkadza mi to.
So, what do you think of doing things this way, Dr. Tenma?
Co pan myśli o tym rozwiązaniu, doktorze Tenma?
Oh, never mind. Don't tell me.
Nieważne, niech pan nic nie mówi.
You're going to that rose mansion now, aren't you?
Idzie pan do tej willi róż, prawda?
Yes.
Tak.
You may finally be close to your goal.
Być może zbliży to pana do celu.
No, I'm not so sure.
Nie byłbym tego taki pewien.
I'm sure you wouldn't listen if I told you not to be rash.
Pewnie nie posłucha pan porady, żeby nie działać pochopnie.
However, just don't die.
Ale proszę nie umierać.
Mr. Grimmer.
Panie Grimmer.
Like we promised when we crossed the Czech border,
Obiecaliśmy sobie przy czeskiej granicy,
when we meet again somewhere, let's have a picnic.
że jeśli się spotkamy, urządzimy sobie piknik.
We'll fish for trout in a beautiful spot…
Będziemy łowić pstrąga w malowniczym miejscu
and enjoy good wine and cheese.
i cieszyć się dobrym winem i serem.
Let's meet again.
Spotkajmy się!
I guess from now on, I'll always be frightened by that sound.
Pewnie już zawsze będę się bał tego odgłosu.
Give it back!
Oddawajcie!
Ow! It hurts!
Auć! Boli!
It hurts!
Boli!
What's wrong? Let me see that.
Co się stało? Pokaż!
Ouch!
Auć!
It's just a scrape.
To tylko zadrapanie.
I'll put some disinfectant on it.
Odkażę je.
Ouch!
Auć!
You're a big boy. Tough it out.
Duży z ciebie chłopak. Wytrzymaj.
There. You're very brave.
Proszę. Odważny chłopak.
Kenzo Tenma, right?
Kenzo Tenma, prawda?
We're the police.
Policja.
Come with us to the station.
Zapraszam z nami na komendę.